<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: datascience | Software, Physics, Data, Mountains]]></title>
  <link href="http://markmims.com/blog/categories/datascience/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://markmims.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-07-10T10:47:29-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://markmims.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark M Mims, Ph.D.]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Educational Components]]></title>
    <link href="http://markmims.com/datascience/2015/10/16/educational-components.html"/>
    <updated>2015-10-16T17:50:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://markmims.com/datascience/2015/10/16/educational-components</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m trying to frame the most basic and naive understanding of education and
learning.  The goal is to have something amenable to various machine learning
techniques… mostly just to see what comes out.</p>

<!--more-->

<hr />

<p>Let’s save the world… it’s simple, quit your job and go teach middle-school
math.  No, seriously.  If you have any sort of quantitative background, it’s
most likely the best way to effectively contribute to society.</p>

<p>Well, I don’t really have the kind of patience it takes to work with kids, so
I’d like to apply a little more leverage to the situation.</p>

<p>Ok, so</p>

<h2 id="the-goal">The Goal</h2>

<p>Apply AdTech to Education.</p>

<p>Specifically</p>

<p>So I’ve always maintained that if you have any sort of quantitative background
and an itch to save the world, you </p>

<hr />

<p>I taught Physical Science at UT for, hell, pretty much my entire tenure in grad
school.  During that time, I spent a lot of time and effort trying to find
better ways of explaining things, better ways to reach people, better ways to
connect physics concepts to my student’s everyday lives.  Ok, so maybe all I
really did was spend my time and energy battling math anxiety, but that’s
another discussion.</p>

<p>In any case, I spent time thinking about the subject itself and how to make it
simpler, that I never really explicitly thought about the learner, the learning
process, variations in learning, etc etc.  I figured if you danced and sang and
explained each thing six ways to Sunday, then you’d get something through the
fog eventually.</p>

<p>So here’s my first pass at understanding education.</p>

<h2 id="activity">activity</h2>

<h3 id="characteristic-functions">characteristic functions</h3>

<p>A characteristic function for a set is useful in analysis when you’re trying to
measure things about that set.  It’s a common tool used in signal processing,
it’s used to define Lebesgue integration, used in PDEs for various transforms,
etc.</p>

<p>It’s a simple function</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

    \phi_A(x) = 
      \left\{
        \begin{array}{ll}
          1 & \mbox{if } x \in A \\
          0 & \mbox{otherwise }
        \end{array}
      \right.
 %]]&gt;</script>

<p>that takes a value of <code>1</code> for any domain entry that’s 
a member of the set <code>A</code>, <code>0</code> otherwise.</p>

<p>Now we can integrate a characteristic function over intervals and establish
some notion of size of the set</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
    \mbox{size of A} = \int_A \phi_A(x) dx.
</script>

<p>Ok, so what does all this have to do with education and learning?</p>

<p>Well, I’ll make an assumption that we can define learning, define learning
activity, and also determine when a student is engaged in a learning activity
or not at any given moment.</p>

<p>Let’s define a function similar to a characteristic function
that identifies learning activity over time.
I.e., define <code>activity</code> as a function</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
    \alpha \colon R_+ \rightarrow [0,1]
</script>

<p>where</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

    \alpha(t) = 
      \left\{
        \begin{array}{ll}
          1 & \mbox{if student is actively learning} \\
          0 & \mbox{otherwise }
        \end{array}
      \right\}.
 %]]&gt;</script>

<p>This function is on (1) when learning is occurring… off (0) when not.
There’s no accounting here for partial engagement.
I’m also totally still being vague about what learning or learning
activity might mean for the moment.  We’ll come back to this in a bit.</p>

<p>Let’s extend the notion of activity to include content or
subject via tagging…</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
    \alpha \colon R_+ \times \lbrace\mbox{tags}\rbrace \to [0,1],
</script>

<p>so we’re really dealing with</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
    \alpha_{\lbrace{\mbox tags}\rbrace}(t).
</script>

<h3 id="example-college-curriculum">Example: college curriculum</h3>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
